Now last but not least there's one other change I want to show you.
imdi son ama en az deil, size gstermek istediim bir baka deiiklik var.
In the app.js file, we get all these lifecycle methods which I explain to you throughout this module. Now
Ve aslnda tm bu yaam dngs yntemlerini aldmz anladm ki bu modlden
react 16.3 actually discourages the usage of three of them and adds two new ones
size imdi aklayacam 16 serbesttir aslnda serbest kalmann kullanmn engeller ve yenilerini ekler.
but step by step. Which ones should you try to avoid?
Ama adm adm hangileri beyaz denemelisiniz.
These are componentWillMount, componentWillUpdate and componentWillReceive props.
Bunlar, bileenlerin gncellenecei bir bileen olacak ve bileen sahne alacak.
Now why are these three discouraged? They are discouraged because they often were used incorrectly.
imdi neden bu zgrler cesaretsizler ki, ou zaman yanl kullanldklar iin cesaretleri krld.
You could call set state in there and possibly the first the first render you could do bad things in
Orada set durumu arayabilirsin ve muhtemelen ilk nce oradaki kt eyleri
there.
yapabilirsin.
This is also the reason why we rarely use these three in this course as you will see in the course project
Bu, ayn zamanda, bu kursta bu zgrl nadiren kullanmamzn sebebi de, ina etmek zere olduumuz
we're about to build,
kurs projesinde greceiniz gibi.
they're not that useful and they're easy to be used incorrectly.
Bu kadar kullanl deiller ve yanl kullanlmalar ok kolay.
So you can still use them,
Yani bunlar hala kullanabilirsiniz.
it will still work, it's not insecure but it's discouraged, react offers two new ones though.
Hala ie yaramayacak, gvensiz deil, ama yine de yenilerini yeniden harekete geirme teklifleri cesaretini krd.
The first new lifecycle hook it adds is getDerivedStateFromProps and this will get the next props
Ekledii ilk yeni yaam dngs kancas sahne alanndan tretilmi bir durumdur ve bu bir sonraki sahne
and the previous state.
ve nceki durumu alacaktr.
Now this lifecycle hook is executed whenever your props are updated and it gives you a chance of updating
Artk bu yaam dngs kancas, sahne dzeniniz gncellendiinde ve sizin durumunuz arasnda durumunuzu gncelleme
your state amongst with them.
ans saladnda yrtlr.
Now often you don't want this,
imdi ou zaman bunu istemiyorsun.
your state should rarely be coupled to your props,
Eyaletiniz nadiren sahne alanlarnza bal olmaldr.
these should be two independent things. But sometimes you get cases where you receive new props and you
Bunlar iki bamsz ey olmal, ancak bazen yeni sahne aldnz durumlar alyorsunuz
want to update your local state because maybe you want to work with that state, you want to change it
ve yerel durumunuzu gncellemek istiyorsunuz nk bir kullanc gvenli bir dmeyi
in that component before a user clicks a save button and you commit it up the state tree, the component tree
tklamadan nce bu bileenle deitirmek istediiniz bu durumda almak isteyebilirsiniz. Uygulamanzdaki  bileenli devleti tamamladktan
in your app and then you change it somewhere else and therefore you will change your props again.
sonra baka bir yerde deitirdiyseniz, cretsiz olarak deiecek veya yeniden ynlendirileceksiniz.
So lets simply add a console log statement in here
Yani burada sadece bir konsol kilitleme ifadesi ekleyelim.
and we're inside at getDerivedStateFromProps and we can output the previous state here
Ve biz, bizden tretilmi durumu elde edebilmek iin ierideyiz ve nceki durumu buradan karabiliriz.
and now as I said, in here, you also should return a new state so this can be object which will be merged
Ve imdi herhangi bir yl dediin gibi, hepiniz geri dnmelisiniz ve siz de devletin bu eski devletle birletirilecei gibi,
with the old state, just like set state calls to it but you can also of course return the old state
devlet arlar gibi eski bir devletle birletirilebilecek bir nesne olabilirsiniz, ancak siz de eski durumu
in which case you'll never update it because you always take the last one.
iade edebilirsiniz. Asla gncellendi nk her zaman sonuncusunu alrsn.
But you could take the props, do something with them and return a new state object which would be used
Ama sahne almak, onlarla bir eyler yapmak ve yerine kullanlacak yeni bir devlet
instead.
nesnesi dndrmek olabilir.
So now we have this set up,
Yani imdi bu kurulumumuz var.
one thing to make this work is we actually have to use the static keyword in front of this because it's
Bu ii yapmak iin bir ey aslnda statik bir anahtar kelime nk statik bir anahtar
a static method,
kelime kullanmak zorundayz.
so basically a method which is not attached to a single instance. With that, if we now reload our app
Temel olarak, tek bir rnee eklenmeyen bir yntem, eer imdi uygulamanz yeniden yklersek, bu uyary
we get that warning because we're using a new lifecycle hook whilst also using two old ones
alrz, nk iki eskiyi de kullanrken yeni bir yaam dngs kullanyoruz.
but that's fine.
Ama bu iyi.
More interesting is that here we see that getDerivedStateFromProps call when we actually loaded
Daha ilgin olan, biz aslnda bizim app yklediimiz zaman prop'n arsndan tretilmi
our app and this of course is well very useful to see.
olsun ve tabii ki grmek iin ok yararl olduunu gryoruz.
It's called before it's actually rendering this
Bunu aslnda oluturmadan nce denir.
and before it's mounting this, it gives us a chance of updating our state right before it does these steps
Ve bunu monte etmeden nce, bize adm admlarn tescil ettirmeden nce durumumuzu
and it will re-execute whenever our props change.
gncelleme ans veriyor ve prodksiyonumuz deitiinde yrtmeyi okuyacaktr.
Again not something you should overuse but definitely nice if you've got a component that needs to bring
Yine bir ey deil, devlet getirmek ve eitleme sahne gerektiren bir bileeni
state and props in sync.
varsa, ar kullanmalsnz ama kesinlikle gzel.
The second new lifecycle which was added is getSnapshotBeforeUpdate.
Eklenen ikinci yeni yaam dngs gncellemeden nce anlk grnt alr.
Now this allows you to get a snapshot of your dom right before it's about to change,
imdi bu, deimek zere olana kadar yurtunuzun anlk grntsn almanza izin veriyor.
so if you got some changes in your component which need to change to the dom, this lifecycle hook will
Bu yzden, bileeninizde bir Dom deerine gemesi gereken baz deiiklikler varsa, mrn tamamlayana
be executed right before the dom does update.
kadar ilk kullanm emberi kancas alr.
So here we can also console log something, we can console log that name
Bu yzden, bu isimde iptal edebileceimiz bir eyi de konserve edebiliriz.
and if we save that and we reload our app, we don't actually see anything here but if I click show persons,
Ve eer bunu kaydedersek ve uygulamamz yeniden yklersek, aslnda burada hibir ey grmyoruz.
we see it here, getSnapshotBeforeUpdate and this executes right before componentDidUpdate is done
Ancak Kiileri gster'i tklarsak, burada gncellemeden nce anlk grnt alrz ve bu, bir bileenin yakalama bileeni iin
for the app.js component.
gncelleme yaplmadan hemen nce yrtlr.
So this is a great place to for example save the current scrolling position of your user.
Yani bu, rnein bir kullancnn bulunduunuz kayma pozisyonunu kaydetmek iin harika bir yerdir.
This can be very useful because in getSnapshotBeforeUpdate,
Bu ok yararl olabilir, nk gncellemeden nce snapchat alr.
you can save it before the dom changes and in componentDidUpdate, you could scroll the user back to the
afakta deiiklik yapmadan nce kaydedebilir ve bileen gncellemesinde kullancy daha nce kaydedilmi konuma
previously saved position for example. Let's say you have a list of items, you add new list items
geri dndrebilirsiniz. rnein, eklediiniz elerin bir listesini gryorsunuz ve buradaki
here you can save scrolling positions before they are added
eleri ekledikten sonra kaydrma konumlarn kaydedebilirsiniz.
and here you can set the users scrolling to that position after they have been added.
Ve burada, kullanc eklendikten sonra o konuma kaydrmay ayarlayabilirsiniz.
This also is the exact example you see in the official docs in the official blog posts on the new
Resmi belgelerde grdnz bu tam rnekte, yeni srmdeki resmi blok
version to be precise. There,
yaynlarnda kesin olarak var.
if you click on that getSnapshotBeforeUpdate link, you get the detailed documentation
Gncelleme balantsn tklamadan nce anlk grntsn tklarsanz ayrntl belgelere sahip olursunuz.
and there you see that example with the scrolling position that is saved.
Ve orada, kaydettiiniz kaydrma pozisyonu ile bu rnei gryorsunuz.
So this is a nice utility you can now also use
Yani bu imdi de kullanabileceiniz gzel bir yardmc programdr.
and that's about it.
Ve bu konuda.
These are great new features introduced by react 16.3
Bunlar, yeniden harekete gemeyen 16 yeni cretsiz zellikler.
If you're using the version, please play around with them and feel three to use them in your next project.
Bu kelimeyi kullanyorsanz, ltfen onlarla oynayn ve bir sonraki projenizde kullanmaktan ekinmeyin.